Finding Aid for Michigan Public Health Association records, 1921-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Public Health Association records 1921-1989
Michigan Public Health Association.
21 linear feet
851869 Bf.4 2
Minutes of board of directors, and house of delegates, reports of annual conferences, treasurer's records, newsletters, miscellaneous topical files, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were deposited by the Michigan Public Health Association (Donor no. 5471 ) beginning in 1975.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Public Health Association was organized in 1919 and incorporated in 1921. In 1936, the Board of Directors stated that, "the primary objective of the Association is the coordination of all professional and lay groups in the promotion of an effective public health program for Michigan."
The Association underwent a major reorganization in 1970. According to the 1985 bylaws, the purposes of the organization are: to promote public health in the state of Michigan; to conduct or sponsor research in public health and allied fields; to disseminate information concerning developments in public health and allied fields; to promote the development or improvement of services for the treatment or prevention of disease; and to promote, encourage, and assist in continuing educational endeavors in the public health field. The Association is composed of the Executive Committee, Board of Directors, House of Delegates, Regional Affiliates, Committees, and Divisions.
The records of the Michigan Public Health Association have been received in various accessions containing similar kinds of documentation. These accessions usually span a specific period of time (with the inclusion of earlier material). This arrangement requires the researcher interested in minutes or newsletters (for example) to examine the total finding aid for similar kinds of materials. The first and also the largest accession contains materials for the period of 1921 to 1973. The dates of the subsequent accessions are 1963-1977 (mainly for 1973-1976), 1952-1986 (mainly for 1952-1986), 1984-1988; and 1983-1989.
Important kinds of records found within most of these dated accessions include minutes of the board of directors, records of conferences, committees, and divisions, and topical files detailing organizational programs and activities.
Subjects:
Michigan Public Health Association.; Public health--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Michigan Public Health Association.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Organizational records
  - 1921-1973
    - Board of Directors Minutes
      - 1921-1965, 7 folders (Box 1)
      - 1965-1970, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - House of Delegates Meetings
      - 1956-1967, 2 volumes (Box 2)
      - 1968-1970, 1 volumes (Box 3)
    - Annual Conferences Reports
      - 1921-1965, 44 reports; 5 volumes (Box 3)
    - Committee Files 1963-1973 (A-Z) (Box 4)
    - Topical Files 1965-1973
      - American Public Health Association 1969-1972 (Box 5)
      - Divisions/Action Councils 1970-1973 (Box 5)
      - Annual Meetings 1965-1971 (Box 5)
      - Annual Meetings 1969-1972 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous files 1969-1972
      - Newsletter (Box 7)
      - Publicity Campaign (Box 7)
      - Biographical Sketches (Box 7)
      - House of Delegates (Box 7)
      - Board of Directors (Box 7)
      - Michigan Association for Community Health (Box 7)
      - Analysis of Legislative Bills (Box 7)
      - Agendas (Box 7)
      - Northern Regional Conference (Box 7)
      - Michigan Health Officers Association (Box 7)
      - Michigan Association of Boards of Health (Box 7)
      - Resolutions (Box 7)
      - Reinstein, Norbert (Box 7)
    - Treasurer's Records (Box 8)
    - Treasurer's Records (Box 9)
    - Division Files
      - Records and Statistics (Box 9)
      - Nutrition (Box 9)
    - Recruitment and Training Committee (Box 10)
    - Environmental Health Section (Box 10)
    - Association Minutes (Box 10)
    - Honorary Membership Committee Nominating Committee (Box 10)
    - American Public Health Association Water Study (Box 10)
    - Annual Conference Meetings Newsletters (Box 10)
    - Division Files
      - Community Nursing (Public Health Nursing) (Box 11)
    - Newsletters
      (see also box 17)
      - 1927-1941, 3 volumes (Box 12)
      - 1975-1978 (Box 12)
      - 1986-1988 (Box 12)
  - 1963-1977 1973-1976
    - Committees
      - 1973-1976 (A-P) (Box 12)
      - 1973-1976 (R-Z) (Box 13)
    - Divisions 1973-1976 (A-Z) (Box 13)
    - Topical 1963-1976
      - American Public Health Association 1973-1976 (Box 13)
      - Board of Directors 1963-1976
        - 1963-1971 (Box 13)
        - 1972-1976 (Box 14)
      - Executive Committee 1969-1976 (Box 14)
      - House of Delegates 1972-1975 (Box 14)
      - MPHA By-Laws 1965-1976 (Box 14)
      - Treasurer's Records 1963-1976 (Box 14)
      - Annual Meetings/Programs 1966-1977 (Box 15)
      - Program Committee 1972-1977 (Box 15)
      - Nursing Division 1972-1977 (Box 15)
      - Miscellaneous Historical 1969-1970 (Box 15)
  - 1952-1986 1976-1986
    - Topical Files 1952-1986
      - Annual Meetings 1976-1981, 5 folders (Box 16)
      - Annual Reports 1973-1980, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Board of Directors 1971-1979, 3 folders (Box 16)
      - Early MPHA Materials 1952-1961 (Box 16)
      - Executive Office 1969-1975, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Functions Booklet 1975 (Box 16)
      - General Materials 1971-1979, 4 folders (Box 16)
      - Health Action League (HALE) 1975-1980 (Box 16)
      - Long Range Finances 1974-1976, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Long Range Planning 1979-1982, 3 folders (Box 16)
      - Manual of MPHA 1973-1976, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Maternal and Child Health 1985-1986 (Box 17)
      - Medical Care Division 1971-1975 (Box 17)
      - Membership (APHA Meeting) 1977 (Box 17)
      - Newsletter 1970-1987, 4 folders (Box 17)
        (see also box 12)
      - Nursing Division 1969-1975, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Photographs (Annual Meetings) 1965-1976 (Box 17)
      - President's Files
        - General 1977-1986, 8 folders (Box 17)
        - General 1982-1986, 3 folders (Box 18)
        - APHA Governing Council 1986 (Box 18)
        - Biologic Products Program/MDPH 1979-1986, 2 folders (Box 18)
        - Correspondence 1961-1962 (Box 18)
        - "Infants at Risk" Project 1983-1984, 3 folders (Box 18)
      - Primary Medical Care Conference 1976-1977 (Box 18)
      - Program Committee 1970-1975, 3 folders (Box 18)
      - Public Health Advisory Committee 1956-1958 (Box 18)
      - Regional Affiliate No. 2 1976-1977 (Box 18)
      - Resolutions Committee 1973-1977 (Box 18)
    - Community Health Division ' 1973-1980
      - Annual Meetings 1976-1978 (Box 19)
      - Chairperson 1975-1977, 3 folders (Box 19)
      - General 1975-1980, 5 folders (Box 19)
      - Health Manpower Action Council 1973-1975 (Box 19)
      - Program Committee 1976-1977 (Box 19)
    - Nutrition Division 1961-1981
      - Annual Meetings 1961-1976, 4 folders (Box 19)
      - Board of Directors 1970-1981, 4 folders (Box 19)
      - Chairperson 1975-1979, 8 folders (Box 19)
      - Committees 1976-1977 (Box 19)
      - Correspondence 1973-1981, 4 folders (Box 20)
      - Executive Committee 1977 (Box 20)
      - Financial Reports 1976-1977 (Box 20)
      - Membership Rosters 1968, 1973 (Box 20)
      - Minutes 1971-1976, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Miscellaneous 1966-1984, 3 folders (Box 20)
      - School Bulletin Project 1980 (Box 20)
  - 1984-1988
    - American Public Health Association Mini-grant 1985-1986 (Box 20)
    - Annual Meetings 1984-1988, 5 folders (Box 20)
    - Board of Directors 1985-1988, 4 folders (Box 20)
  - 1983-1989
    (mainly Suzanne Antisdel president's files, 1987-1988)
    - Annual meeting materials 1985-1988 (Box 21)
    - Board minutes 1983-1989, 3 folders (Box 21)
    - Board miscellanea (Antisdel file) 1988-1989 (Box 21)
    - Newsletter: Impact, 1986-1989 (Box 21)
    - President's correspondence (Suzanne Antisdel) 1987-1988 (Box 21)
    - Resolutions 1983-1987 (Box 21)
    - Varia 1979-1984 (Box 21)
  - Ceremonial events
    (Robert Bowman file)
    - MPHA-50th Anniversary Session 1971, 3 folders (Box 21)
      (include slides, script used for slide presentation, sound cassette of speakers at conference, and VHS video cassette of program)
    - "Alive and well in Michigan-A Bicentennial Heritage of Public Health" 1978 (Box 21)
      (include slides, script for slide presentation, and sound cassette of slide presentation)